Finding Aid for the Adrian C. Kanaar M.D. papers Biomed.0106
UCLA Library Special Collections
Adrian C. Kanaar, M.D. papers
1940-2001
UCLA Library Special Collections
Kanaar, Adrian Charles
Biomed.0106
1 Linear Feet (2 boxes)
Dr. Kanaar was a British-born and -trained surgeon who served in the Royal Army Medical Corps during World War II, in France and Belgium up to the retreat at Dunkirk, in various battlefield locations after D-day, and in Berlin during the occupation. This collection focuses mostly on his non-medical writings, namely descriptions of his war experiences in Europe and of the conditions he observed there. Included are several typescripts of two unpublished books: 1. "War-time reflections by a British Army surgeon", which was based partly on a series of talks given by Capt. Kanaar during three months spent in the United States while on special leave; 2. "The Sign of the Hammer and Sickle " which is also partly based on wartime experiences; 3. typescripts of a number of published and unpublished essays, articles, and letters to newspapers. The bulk of the collection dates to 1940-1948.
Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9966614103606533
Acquisition Information
The collection was a gift from Dr. Margaret H. Jones-Kanaar to the UCLA Biomedical Library.
Biography
Adrian C. Kanaar, MD, MRCP (London), FRCS (Edinburgh) (1911-1993) qualified M.B. at St. Bartholomew's Hospital, London, in 1934, received a B.S. from London University in 1936, had surgical training at Edinburgh University, and was awarded the M.D. from the British Postgraduate Medical School in 1939. That year he was called to active service with the Royal Army Medical Corps and was active in France and Belgium through the retreat at Dunkirk; he returned to the Continent after D-Day and served in various stations, including occupied Berlin. On special leave in 1942 in the U.S., Captain Kanaar began a series of talks about his war experiences, wanting to foster Anglo-American cooperation and to clear up what he felt were misconceptions about the war and about the British. These talks evolved into some of the manuscript chapters included in this collection. His experiences in Germany after the war's end, and especially his impressions of the administration in the Russian zone, are described in the second major manuscript in this collection, and in many of the shorter pieces.
In 1948 Dr. Kanaar had the honor of presenting a Hunterian lecture to the Royal College of Surgeons of England. Shortly thereafter he and his wife and son emigrated to Eastern Canada where he practiced orthopedic surgery and physical medicine. In 1959 he moved to Buffalo, NY, to become Director of Physical Medicine, Department of Public Health, and Associate Professor at the University of Buffalo Medical School. In 1964, the year he became a US citizen, the family moved to Poughkeepsie, NY, where he maintained a private practice in physical medicine and rehabilitation until his retirement in 1984. He was active in and cited for community leadership in physical fitness, and was a member of the American College of Sports Medicine. He published widely in the fields of rehabilitation and fitness, and practiced what he preached: as a young man he made two attempts to swim the English Channel, coming within a mile and a half of his goal; at age 74, he swam the 28.5 miles around New York City's Manhattan Island. He stated that the Channel swims were motivated by the wish to demonstrate that a dedicated Christian could also be an athlete and a strong individual.
After the death of his wife of 47 years, Dr. Kanaar retired and moved to Pacific Palisades, California. There he met and married Margaret H. [Holden] Jones, MD in 1989.
Scope and Content
The collection focuses mainly on Dr. Kanaar's non-medical writings for 1940-1948, namely accounts of his experiences and observations in Europe during World War II and the subsequent occupation of Germany. There are various typescripts of two unpublished works, "United we stand: war-time reflections of a British Army surgeon", covering his service from the war's beginning through the evacuation from Dunkirk; and "The sign of the Hammer and Sickle", focusing more on the time of the occupation. Also included are a number of published and unpublished commentaries, letters to newspapers, and articles by Kanaar.
The collection is organized into the following series:
Series 1. Professional Activities. 3 folders
Series 2. Personal Beliefs and Accounts. 12 folders
Series 4. Personal Information. 4 folders
World War, 1939-1945 -- Personal narratives, English.; Physicians -- Personal narratives.; Jones, Margaret Holden; Kanaar, Adrian Charles -- Manuscripts
- Professional Activities, Series 1.; 3 folders
  Scope and Contents note
  materials pertaining to a Hunterian Lecture delivered to the Royal College of Surgeons
  - Application for Hunterian Professorship., 1948 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    original application letter and a follow-up note, both signed by Dr. Kanaar; photocopy of précis for lecture on "Pulmonary atelectasis in general surgery, with special reference to aetiology"
  - "Pulmonary atelectasis in postoperative and traumatic cases: some recent advances", Hunterian Lecture delivered to the Royal College of Surgeons of England by A. C. Kanaar., 1948; 23 l. plus illustrations and tables (Box 1, Folder 2)
    a short "Introduction/Abstract" to the paper by Margaret H. Jones-Kanaar, MD, written after her husband's death; text and illustrations of the lecture; letter from "The Annals of the Royal College of Surgeons of England" regretting inability to publish the lecture because of its length, and suggesting submission to a different journal
  - Early versions of the atelectasis study. (Box 1, Folder 3)
    text and data drafts, lecture notes, case notes
    General note
    mostly undated; some case notes dated 1948
- Personal Beliefs and Accounts, Series 2.; 12 folders
  writings and related materials on: World War II; Russian occupation in Germany and Poland; Communism; Religion
  - "War-time reflections by a British Army surgeon", by Capt. A. C. Kanaar, MD, MRCP (London), FRCS (Edin)., 1940; 92 l. (Box 1, Folder 4)
    quoting from the cover page: "This narrative of one man's early World War II experiences evolved from a series of talks given by Capt. Kanaar during three months spent in America while on special leave because of his wife' illness"; typed copy
  - "United we stand: war-time reflections of a British Army surgeon"., 1943; ca. 73,600 words (Box 1, Folder 5)
    typed draft of a projected book, incorporating Capt. Kanaar's experiences in France up to and through the evacuation of the British Army at Dunkirk (see Folder 4, above) as Part I; Britain during the war (Part II); Looking ahead (Part III)
    missing from this manuscript: Part II, chapters 2-4, 8; Part III, chapters 2, 3, 5-9
  - "United we stand: war-time reflections of a British Army surgeon"., 1943 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    photocopy of the typescript above
  - "The Sign of the Hammer and Sickle", by A. C. Kanaar., undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
    partial typescript of an expanded version of "United we stand"; included are: Preface; Table of contents; Précis of chapters; Chapters 3-6, 8-19
    the paper is in fragile condition, with tears, worn edges, rust stains
  - "The Sign of the Hammer and Sickle", by A. C. Kanaar., undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
    these pages are easier to handle and read
  - "The Sign of the Hammer and Sickle", by A. C. Kanaar., undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
    the most complete version of the projected book, missing only the Foreword promised by Lord Bertrand Russell; included are: Table of Contents; Illustrations, Maps and Cartoons; Preface; Précis of chapters; 19 chapters
  - Alleged Russian misconduct in occupied Germany., 1945-1946; original and photocopy for each item (Box 2, Folder 2)
    manuscript letter from Bertrand Russell to Kanaar; short typed letter from A. C. Russell, Ingham Infirmary, South Shields, to Kanaar; clipping from the weekly periodical "Forward", Glasgow, Dec. 15, 1945, titled "What is happening in Germany? A Scots soldier replies to Bertrand Russell", by Tim Christie; correspondence with the editor of "Forward", and Kanaar's rebuttal to Christie, titled "More about Germany"
    Christie questioned the assertions of Russian misconduct made by Russell in his article "The German Disaster", published in "Forward", Nov. 17, 1945, assertions which Kanaar believed to be true
  - List of articles by A. C. Kanaar published in 1945-1947. (Box 2, Folder 3)
    the list provides dates and names of newspapers/magazines, and the following titles: "Report on Germany"; "The trail of the beast in Holland"; "What I saw in Germany"; "Land reform in Germany"; "The spectre behind the Iron Curtain"; "Why doctors said 'no' to Mr. Bevan"; "What the doctors want"; "The doctors and the State"; "What does Mr. Bevan want?"
  - Unpublished commentaries/articles by Kanaar. (Box 2, Folder 4)
    originals and photocopies of the following items: "Escape to freedom"; "Genocide continues, despite Nuremberg"; "Agrarreform et alia"; "The lake in the wood"; "Denazification of a whole community" [a number of separate observations and comments]
    the focus of all the items is on behavior of Russian troops and administrators in occupied areas of Germany and Poland post World War II
  - Communism. (Box 2, Folder 5)
    typed "Selected bibliography on Communism" [by D. Fetler?], listing items 1935-1962; two sets of manuscript notes, one headed "Communism, peaceful co-existence", the other "Communism past and present, lecture to ???, 1979"
  - Miscellaneous newspaper/magazine clippings on communism and the cold war., 1948-1979 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    items taken from both British and American publications
  - "A physicians faith", by Adrian C. Kanaar., 1987 June 21; 7 l. (Box 2, Folder 7)
    typescript, edited from a talk given at the Baptist Church, Poughkeepsie, New York
- Personal Information, Series 4.; 4 folders
  - Photograph., 1958 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    3x4" portrait of Dr. Kanaar
  - Biographical materials. (Box 2, Folder 9)
    selective list of "Personal particulars", 1911-1947; curriculum vitae, Nov. 1976 (updated to June 1986)
  - Obituary and memorial letter., 1993 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    one-page typed obituary; Christmas letter to Dear Family and Friends, signed Margaret, with snapshots of the Drs. Kanaar and Jones-Kanaar together, and Dr. Kanaar alone
  - Margaret Holden Jones-Kanaar, MD, 1904–2001. (Box 2, Folder 11)
    manuscript letter from Dr. Kanaar's second wife, covering transmittal of additional Kanaar material to the UCLA Biomedical Library, 21 Sep 1994; clipping of Dr. Jones-Kanaar's obituary from the "Los Angeles Times", 12 Dec 2001
    Dr. Margaret Jones-Kanaar was a retired UCLA pediatrician and renowned pioneer in the treatment of cerebral palsy